anybody need take a sip of water if you
woke up at 4:30 sometimes you can
meditate with your eyes slightly open
seriously
keeps you from falling asleep ok
children wore 130 130 we were thinking
to do for offering once a week from
Ellen
just kidding okay let's meditate we can
do that later maybe more money will go
in if you medicate
so please relax your forehead you really
can open your eyes slightly if you feel
sleepy but don't look at anything or if
you feel sleepy halfway through then
crack with your eyes open it's like
relax your fingers stretch them out
stretch stretch stretch stitch and then
chin mudra
pull in your stomach slightly shoulders
back relax and a little bit a smile and
then come to your breath long exhale try
to make the excess each one a little bit
longer
then please invite your heart teacher to
come sit with you in front of you need
to me very close make them alive start
breathing you can smell the fragrance
from their body you can feel their one
and bow down to them by thinking of some
good quality and that they have and just
enjoy just enjoy that good quality just
admire
make them allows me I think today let's
choose something that somebody else did
so it's easy to find and offering the
hard work that people have done to help
us here it's a lot of work to keep this
place ready for us all year long they're
working so we can offer a number this
beautiful seed that opened inside of us
that we have people to help us work too
hard
and then you can
open your heart show your number-one bad
habit that you had that you're
embarrassed to talk about and you can be
honest with your number show it to them
ask for help
then after not to keep teaching
encouraging us to take refuge real
refuge in using seeds of observing
others to make the world happy make
ourselves happy and whole world
then ass kilometer stay in our life
stay in our heart inside the grain of
sugar
then again I'd like to do a meditation
on our plans for the next month so the
month of May is beginning soon and it
seems like a good month to try to
improve our practice by taking refuge so
think of something that we did yesterday
something you would like to achieve I
would like to make more time in my life
to do things I'd like to do so I'm going
to be quiet for a while and you go ahead
and do the four steps for yourself from
a number one you know I would like
something to change in my life and then
number two right I know someone who
would like to same thing something
similar and then number three I can make
a very doable plan to help them specific
learner and then number four I will you
can imagine you can practice a coffee
meditation this morning glad to seem to
do it every night for me in May
okay so I'll be quiet you go ahead and
do your four-step planning and I'll meet
you in about ten minutes
then please ask your llama to come into
your heart let's do it slow you know how
to do it the main thing in the scripture
is that they're really happy that you're
asking for them to stay in your heart so
try to feel how happy they are that you
were practicing how proud of you they
are it's not easy to come to Diamond
Mountain it's not easy to stay here
especially from other countries like New
York and you are your llama is very very
happy that you work so hard to come here
you spend so much money you took your
time and it's not like a five-star hotel
it's many things uncomfortable sometimes
it's difficult to sit in long long
classes and just try to feel how happy
the Buddhists are how happy your nama is
that you worked so hard this week and we
had such beautiful harmony among all the
people here we're all from different
countries we all have different
backgrounds and there's a beautiful
family ceiling here
and I think that makes the Buddhist very
happy it makes your Lama very happy that
everyone worked so hard to have harmony
with everyone else
then come to your breath 3 long exhales
don't open your eyes here
okay then open your pictures alright
let's do a little bit of Lum room you
can I think it's not yeah it's right
below and there we go good alright we're
continuing with the refuge now what was
the first one after you take refuge in
who does don't do stupid refuse like
cellphone reference okay then the second
one after you take refuge in Dharma
don't hurt other people certainly one
else to take refuge in Sangha yeah stick
around with people who irritatingly
remind you of seeds
number four is you know treat all Buddha
images like real Buddha number five is
treat all writing as holy
number six is treat all robust holy even
if the person inside is not so holy
number seven
yeah took about how cool they are
number eight yeah I was watching when we
were drinking before the meditation and
Vivian did a nice offering I didn't but
she was like I was drinking and I said
what's he doing and she's like okay okay
right number nine are you okay cam dog
door lock company it means help others
to take refuge okay help others to take
refuge okay and there's a picture below
there can you show it the wrong way
that's the wrong way Sean oh my god I
mean you have to do that you know that's
the wrong way what's the right way I
heard your husband is yelling at you a
lot let me tell you about emptiness got
it inside his head he's empty right
you know what I mean
second husband okay McDavid Timbers
objects okay is I think it's named
toward honor in Sanskrit it's like you
can say Stephen Hawking the Guru of the
science church
I'm kidding seriously people always
asked him what do you think and he's
like I think there's a black hole from
her with a painter but don't send them
burnt umber Shanna dedicated on day Jay
and joke members talk nominate custom in
one key then actually he says kind of
testing sometimes he's kind of tough
he's more direct and Geshe Michael he
says every time those guys tell you that
copper atoms are carrying your
conversations they're actually creating
a thicker an obstacle in their own life
you see every time they you ask a
scientist how does the cell phone work
and they say Oh electrons are passing
through a copper wire every time they
repeat that lower refuge it gets
stronger in their mind you see so
actually every time they talk about
science it's actually hurting them you
see they mean they don't understand
where the copper electrons came from
okay and we're going to see in common uh
Sheila why those atoms are impossible
right okay and that wrong idea started I
think with Aristotle just before is
Donald but it gets stronger right all
right Shannon Kelso silly monkey Nina
Mustafa Chantal I think I'm a better
break I think now I like this next sent
it slam to children next sentence Lander
children WA okay those are my own notes
okay that I made in the last few months
Longman's on the past tea means to help
them get on the past rule okay the one
means people whose minds are open they
are when you call it receptive okay
like you meet somebody on a plane or at
a yoga class and they say what are you
what are you doing and they seem like
pretty nice person and if they are rulla
rulla means they're open they are
receptive they just didn't hear about it
yet
okay they can accept it or they would be
interested to start learning then if you
feel this person is wrong then share
don't tell right share with them say
look I learned this thing from this guy
named takapa and if you could pronounce
his name you become a Buddhist not just
kidding and I think it's good to say
look I don't follow it 100% you know I'm
not super successful but I tried to use
the four steps and I got some good
results and I'm not perfect and I don't
understand it perfectly and it's it's a
lot to understand it's like an ocean you
know but I try I did my best and you
want to have tea together and I'll tell
you about this four-step thing and and
you try it and if it works you you do
more and if it doesn't work just forget
it okay I like this some mama's who say
it that way
you know just give it a try four steps
if it works you can do more if it
doesn't work you know you're just a nice
person for a few weeks okay all right
my friends used to ask me my family say
what did Buddhism do for you good night
my mother and father were both alcoholic
so I have generic alcoholic you know if
I not careful I will be alcoholic so I
said and they both died from alcohol and
then I said if Buddhism didn't teach me
anything else but I learned not to drink
alcohol you know all those many years of
study and many books and many teachings
maybe it's all wrong but they taught me
not to drink alcohol so that's worth it
I didn't diet my mom died in her 42 or
something from alcohol my father died
similar okay then I didn't I'm older so
I always say you know just tell your
friend look I don't know it's 100
percent correct I'm not super Buddhist
you know meditator usually when I
meditate I meditate about lunch my green
drink
[Music]
but it's cool maybe you want our time
okay so that's vowel number nine you
know turn on other people who are open
but don't bother people who are not open
till rule number K shorts in check digit
short is cool Adam a'ready k Tom means
when you just having an informal
conversation you know Quecha then sure
means insert it in the conversation okay
sure means by the way like if you say
Gail say keen on La Ceiba Shana an ego
bonnet in I was headed for Kelsey's
house and then on the way by the way I
dropped off at the community center okay
so Charlotte means by the way
so you're just talking to somebody in a
coffee shop shwarma
insert in the conversation you know you
can say like this do you like the
kasnian they say yeah then you say do
you know about the four steps like
smooth transition to the Kentucky energy
Bergen and Camden AR can do like
dopamine's help them to understand
message the real reference okay the
second husband okay
welcome we on him okay number ten
payment and egg on England from ten land
I'm sorry
new momentum ten ransom DMC Johnny
quarrelsome acarnania not inventing new
top Anita back a day me intend to do to
come Sidonians were supposed to take
roughly six times a
three times during the daylight three
times during the dark so it's harder in
the summer to do all the nighttime work
right if you understand what Russians is
you don't have to worry about this vow
why at least six times a day somebody
will irritate you okay at least six
times a day you will have some kind of
problem and then you take refuge and say
you know I don't know this person said
something bad to me this person to put
something bad about getting Michael on
the Internet
okay why you know maybe I thought it
Louie CK do you know Maurice in case
it's a comedian American comedian he
says these guys went to Afghanistan you
know and people start shooting they are
American soldiers people start shooting
guns at them maybe it's because they're
shooting other people so someone could
his size gets him back on the Internet
Geshe Michael judging people all day you
know 10 times a day and 20 times a day
30 times a day secretly you know he's a
nice guy so he has to do it quietly
inside here I don't know oh okay maybe
maybe I caused it like that then you
took refuge
that's one then only five more you can
think about the same irritating person
again after an hour why do you put that
stuff on the internet about me oh yeah
me I judge people okay like that okay so
if you really understand refuge it's
easy to dis about no problem in English
we have an idiom no brainer easy super
easy anybody can do no brainer okay all
right I have to teach them English
idioms every day they're supposed to
teach me Chinese but they gave up on you
and the council join you
alright number eleven tower can chicken
cordial or local McKinney challenge
industry chicken
whether you're doing something major or
whether you're doing something minor
kondou-san Marlow Celtic put all your
trust in the three jewels okay it means
in the fourth day
tell me congealed octopus and a coupon a
song and yogi Tom Jun ji-hyun ten more
Han Solo come to me table then try to
make it a habit so this is all about
making it a habit to think about the
real causes of things okay that's all
make it a habit to think about the real
causes of things okay all day long and
don't take those lower try to reduce
your lower refuge in science or other
things like that okay
psychology okay number 12
last one we did it join Joe soon so come
tarneja get joonyoung me pony the last
one is don't give up refuge okay don't
give up refuge I think it's not
difficult okay but I've seen some people
do it right we know some people right
they studied here for five six seven
years and and then they got discouraged
and they give up those are the people
who write me emails when they get cancer
you know like 10 years later 20 years
later after missing 25 long memory trees
they write me again they say oops I
boo-boo
I'm a mistake I gave up refugee no now
will help me I said it's too late man
what you want me to teach 25 retreats
again you know it's too late okay don't
don't write don't write me after 20
years and tell me you made a mistake
okay this guy came to me he said you
remember me I said no she said I was in
the class at Rinpoche my teacher he came
to the class when there are only five
students I said oh yeah now I remember
you
he said I wasted my whole life you used
your life I wasted my life you know he
was in the first class with my momma
he said waited my whole life you know so
don't don't be like that okay all right
come down to LA number ten a promotion
if you stopped thinking of that things
are made from your seeds you get what
you call kicked out a boost
okay by yourself nope nobody what do you
call that when you kick somebody on a
religion yeah nobody excommunicate means
to kick somebody out of the religion you
are not a good person now you are no
more Christian or you're no more juries
but in Buddhism it it's not the
authorities of the church who kick you
out it's yourself when your self
excommunication so some things are self
existing so it means you you give up
that way of thinking
it doesn't mean you say I don't like
doing anymore something like remember my
inner get too long dong Chan soos
ability to sum up a young member GUI if
you're not a Buddhist you can't be a
monk if you're not a Buddhist you can't
be a bodhisattva if you're not a
Buddhist you can't practice diamond way
secret teachings Kendall don't own a
song Joo Min Young
so generally not taking refuge
technically is not on the list of ways
that you can lose your bells but
practically speaking it's it's the same
thing if you give up the foundation then
you lose your Bodhisattva vows you lose
your tenderness okay
what's the foundation yeah just think
like that okay when you stop thinking
like that there's no foundation for your
vows anymore okay so all these people
are worried about how long your hair is
you know it's supposed to be this long
if you're more than ten miles from the
monastery it's supposed to be this long
is here you know or they're worried
about do you have a blue stripe here or
not
if you don't have a blue stripe you're
not real till copper follower all these
people worry about the outside things
right but that's not what makes your
marker okay
it's your did you take refuge or not
it's your thinking okay think like a
Hmong then you can still go to the mall
and buy nice clothes you don't have to
wear the same thing every day
okay then you're they call a dum-dum
begin on say dum-dum be gentle don't
dump a give them in a be double crochet
Stanley's translating ultimate mums
ultimate none is a person who
understands the pen okay higher than
normal higher than normal none okay then
dumb beginner ultimate some ultimate
ultimate none anyone who understands a
pen okay higher more higher now and they
we're just out of miniskirts and Templar
seed and sing songs
I like it thank you okay
Dana tell us sake to numb to a lot
tamashii gay then in the lamb real we
say you know everybody's waiting for a
chance to keep this Val this is where
somebody from the Immigration Department
ties you up and says I'm going to kill
you if you don't give up Buddha you know
okay
we're all waiting to show we can be a
martyr
I don't care you could kill me now okay
but then he says be careful because
really sometimes just making a joke you
can give it up okay so be careful just
making jokes about Buddhism and be
careful Buddhism is very powerful stuff
so you can make it jokes about
politicians or people who aren't
Buddhist
okay in in Christian we have the word
goddamnit
okay and it's a bad word and you're
using the word God for bad thing so
that's the same thing in in in Tibetan
how do you say god dammit no you didn't
say it right crews young it means three
and when you say it that way it means
God Danny okay so be careful
one time I saw Tibetan say that I asked
my Lama what what he's angry but he's
saying three jewels he says don't learn
it don't learn it then foreign people
like to learn bad words right like oh
you know tell me what it means you know
then you explain Five Diamond words or
one bad word they learned the bad word I
don't know la même Timberlane then he
quotes the LA branch mo sake Jeremy told
ongoing Yellin ECAM de la Mer you know
so this is the big one he says this vow
is probably very important it means to
stop thinking about seeds okay you lost
refugee station to congestion math on
yonder dr. Minton determined also
presume non means in China and he says
less dangerous but also dangerous is to
split your refuge of 50% science 50%
causes okay
generally everything's coming from me
generally you know things come from
Karma but not WeChat which others self
existence
okay we tack came from itself the things
very important in your life
oh those like don't come from me okay
okay
like that so don't split your refuge go
this way I go this way
have some courage accepted a hundred
percent or do the do science for a while
being miserable come back later okay
sending me Mardan girls and candle no
McElroy don't laugh okay I'm gonna go we
reached a very we we actually covered
what we're supposed to cover that's very
unusual
so Tim I'm ready if you have other stuff
but I'm going to do one more sentence
what's the three signs of a good teacher
know the material wealth know the
students well let the class out early
okay makes a popular kitchen okay so we
have one more part then we reach the
thirteenth day of the original teaching
okay so that's a very good place to stop
before Guadalajara don't forget to come
to beautiful Mexico the weather there is
not like Diamond Moses it's always
perfect
the weather in Guadalajara change is 10
degrees all year its garden city of
Mexico and we've stayed leg to plumber
which I used to call leg caliper because
I can't remember okay but come to elect
upon a very very beautiful place we're
going to try to have a yoga training
after the lumber-room
okay for five days so we'll send you
when it's confirm we'll send your
announcement I didn't teach people how
to teach yoga for ten years or something
but if you have time you can do both at
the same go to love em and then stay for
the yoga teacher training if you want
okay
DCR yoga teacher training new goomar did
I make a mistake introduction to yoga
not real yoga teacher training and we're
trying to bring it's an introduction to
yoga teacher training and we're trying
to bring a hundred Mexican school
teachers on teach them new goomar for
free so they will come to college now we
didn't get the money I'm working on it
okay so soon sake chairman Tony when you
talk about not giving up the three
jewels even at the cost of your life
non-ohmic Guinean Sheila moot even lanky
kid cam doe McDonald such a then there
was a gain and gain Ian means not am
uncle or novice monk but a layperson
who took that refuge fell okay then
some people caught him or her I don't
know who it was and they said if you
don't give up three jewels we will kill
you and then what happened gained Yankee
Candle mocked our he refused or she
wishes they don't say he or she would
think they say and they killed him okay
Scioto killer then he was born in
kishida
okay not bad maybe try to get caught by
the Immigration Department okay then the
Lama did some review and we went home
for the bag